A Guide to the Robert A. Belz Papers, 1869, 1929-1962, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Robert A. Belz Papers, 1869, 1929-1962, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2011-105
0.8 cu. ft. 2 boxes; 5 folders
The Robert A. Belz Papers contain personal and academic materials collected and created during 1869-1962. Belz graduated from Virginia in 1939 with a Bachelors degree in Industrial Engineering. Papers include coursework, newspaper clippings, and photographs.
Belz, Robert Armstrong
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Robert A. Belz Papers were donated to Special Collections prior to 2000.
Biographical Note
Robert A. Belz of Staunton, Va., entered Virginia Tech as a freshmen in 1934. Belz was a member of the University's Corps of Cadets, and majored in Industrial Engineering. He graduated in 1939.
Scope and Content
The collection contains the personal and academic papers of Robert A. Belz, a 1939 Virginia Tech alumni who graduated with a bachelors degree in industrial engineering. Materials range from 1869-1962, however, a majority of the works are from the 1930s-1940s or undated. Several oversized folders accompany the collection and hold technical drawings, newspapers, or posters. In addition to school work for math, business, humanities, and science courses, the collection also includes correspondence, clippings and ephemera, and a small group of photographs and cards.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in five series: Academic Papers, Correspondence, Ephemera, Newspapers Clippings, and Photographs and Illustrations. All five series include subseries organized by subject and/or material type. Within each subseries, materials are arranged in chronological order wherever possible. Undated materials can be found at the back of folders. All oversized materials are in folders.
Series I: Academic Papers consists of the undergraduate and graduate work of Robert A. Belz. This includes, but is not limited to: tests, notes, and notebooks. Most notably, there is an extensive, oversized collection of sketches from Belz's geometry and engineering classes. The series is further divided into seven subseries which organize materials based on subject. The seven subseries are: Business, Corps of Cadets, Engineering, General, Humanities, Math, and Science.
Series II: Correspondence is divided into two subseries. Subseries A: Academic comprises Belz's academic letters and memos such as transcripts and orientation documents. Subseries B: Personal consists of Belz's personal correspondence papers which range from dental appointment postcards to church meeting invitations.
Series III: Ephemera accommodates various items from Belz's collegiate life. The series is divided into two subseries, Academic and Student Life. A 1934 Virginia Tech Directory and a marketing poster for a "V.P.I. Skippers" dance are two examples of the material within this series.
Series IV: Newspaper Clippings consists of dated Clippings and undated Clippings. Both groupings contain a diverse array of newspaper articles, and in some cases, full periodicals. The subjet matter is both serious and frivolous. Topics range from the construction of the Pentagon to the "types of girls in a powder room."
Series V: Photographs and Illustrations contain three folders based on material type: Christmas Cards, Illustrations, and Photographs.
Index Terms
Persons:
Belz, Robert Armstrong
Subjects:
University Archives; Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State Univeristy. College of Engineering.; Virginia Polytechnic Institute. Alumni Association
Contents List
- Series I: Academic Papers, 1933-1951, n.d.
  - Subseries A: Business, 1937-1939 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Subseries: B: Corps of Cadets, 1934-1935, n.d. (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Subseries C: Engineering, 1933-1951, n.d.
    - Academic Papers, Engineering I (Box-folder 1-3)
    - Academic Papers, Engineering II (Box-folder 1-4)
    - Academic Papers, Engineering III (Box-folder 1-5)
    - Academic Papers, Engineering Drawings (Folder 1)
  - Subseries D: General, 1934-1936, n.d.
    - Academic Papers, General I (Box-folder 1-6)
    - Academic Papers, General II (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Subseries E: Humanities, 1934, 1951, n.d.
    - Academic Papers, Humanities I (Box-folder 1-8)
    - Academic Papers, Humanities II (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Subseries F: Math, 1934-1936, n.d. (Box-folder 1-10)
    - Academic Papers, Math (Box-folder 1-10, Folder 2)
  - Subseries G: Science, 1933-1935, 1938, n.d.
    - Academic Papers, Science I (Box-folder 2-1)
    - Academic Papers, Science II (Box-folder 2-2)
    - Academic Papers, Science III (Box-folder 2-3)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1869, 1935-1952, n.d.
  - Subseries A: Academic, 1934-1952 n.d (Box-folder 2-4)
  - Subseries B: Personal, 1869, 1936-1952, n.d. (Box-folder 2-5)
- Series III: Ephemera, 1929-1961, n.d.
  - Subseries A: Academic, 1929-1939, n.d.
    - Ephemera, Academic I (Box-folder 2-6)
    - Ephemera, Academic II (Box-folder 2-7)
  - Subseries B: Student Life, 1931-1932, 1961-1962, n.d.
    - Ephemera, Student Life (Box-folder 2-8)
    - Ephemera, Student Life (Folder 3)
- Series IV: Newspaper Clippings, 1934-1953, n.d.
  - Dated Clippings, 1934-1953
    - Newspaper Clippings, Dated Clippings I (Folder 4)
    - Newspaper Clippings, Dated Clippings II (Folder 5)
  - Undated Clippings (Box-folder 2-9)
- Series V: Photographs and Illustrations, 1932, 1941, n.d.
  - Christmas Cards, n.d. (Box-folder 2-10)
  - Illustrations, 1941, n.d (Box-folder 2-11)
  - Photographs, 1932, n.d (Box-folder 2-12)